United States War Relocation Authority papers, 1942-1946
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
United States War Relocation Authority Collection, 1942-1946
MS 042
United States -- Army -- Regimental Combat Team -- 442nd -- Photographs
Publications, reports, manuals, correspondence, photographs, and other materials relating mainly to the internment of Japanese Americans during World War II.
9 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Historical Note
The U.S. War Relocation Authority was responsible for the relocation, internment, and reintegration of Japanese and Japanese Americans during World War II. From 1942 to 1946, Edward H. Spicer, Anthropology professor at the University of Arizona, was Head of the Community Analysis Section of the War Relocation Authority, in Washington, D.C.
Organization
This collection is organized into nine series:
Series I: General Files, 1942-1946
Series II: Newspapers, 1943-1947
Series III: Community Analysis Section Publications, 1943-1946
Series IV: Statistic Reports, 1943-1945
Series V: Correspondence, 1942-1946
Series VI: Relocation Center Documents, 1943-1946
Series VII: Photographs, 1942-1945
Series VIII: War Relocation Authority Publications and Reports, 1943-1946
Series IX: Government Documents Relating to War Relocation Authority, 1942-1946
Scope and Content Note
Publications, reports, manuals, correspondence, photographs, and other materials relating mainly to the internment of Japanese Americans during World War II.
The largest group of material encompasses Community Analysis Reports from 11 individual relocation centers. The centers were located in Poston and Rivers, Ariz.; Denson and Rohwer, Ark.; Manzanar and Newell, Calif.; Amache, Colo.; Hunt, Idaho; Oswego, N.Y.; Topaz, Utah; and Heart Mountain, Wyo. The center at Oswego, N.Y. housed war refugees from southern Europe.
The next largest group of materials is comprised of official W.R.A. pamphlets, as well as typescript studies by various W.R.A. personnel, including Spicer. These studies are often concerned with sociological issues such as racism, the effects of center life on the evacuees, and their attitudes about Japan. Among the newspapers, two are in Japanese: the "Washington Daily News Digest," 1945, and an issue of the "Doho," 1943, from New York. Incoming and outgoing correspondence relates both to Spicer and John F. Embree, of the Community Analysis Section; also Dillon S. Myer of the W.R.A. Some letters are from the community analysts informally reporting events at the different relocation centers.
Statistic reports include relocations by state, and returns to the West Coast by city. Government documents relate to House and Senate bills and resolutions, cases before the Supreme Court, the administration of alien property, and hearings before the House Committee on Un-American Activities. Among the miscellaneous items are maps, organizational charts, the official administrative manual, information on Buddhism, transcripts of speeches and radio broadcasts, bibliographic citations, and poetry written by center residents. Black-and-white photographs are well-identified by place, photographer, subject, and often individuals' names. They depict the centers; W.R.A. officials; soldiers of the all-Japanese American 442nd Combat Team
Some materials are in Japanese.
Spicer, Edward Holland, 1906- -- Correspondence; Embree, John F. (John Fee), 1908-1950 -- Correspondence; Myer, Dillon S. (Dillon Seymour), 1891- -- Correspondence; United States -- Army -- Regimental Combat Team -- 442nd -- Photographs; World War, 1939-1945 -- Evacuation of civilians -- United States; Concentration camps -- United States; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Japanese Americans -- Photographs; Japanese in the United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Japanese Americans; Land grants -- Arizona; Correspondence; Photographs; Reports
Related Material
Related material is located in the United States Wartime Civil Control Administration Collection (MS 239).
Container List
- Series I: General Files, 1942-1946
  - Administrative Instructions, no. 1-97. 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Bibliographies; Books. 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Buddhism. 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Center Liaison Section. Report. 1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Codes, File Outlines, Slide Lists. 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Community Government. 1942-1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Community School Forum, vol. 1, no. 2-4. June-August 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Conferences. 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Exclusion Papers; Post-Exclusion Bulletin, no. 1-8., 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - F.B.I. Investigations at the Centers. 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Japanese Poetry by Residents of the Centers. 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Juvenile Delinquency. 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Manual and Supplements. 1942-1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Maps; Organization Charts. 1942-1946 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Documents (mimeographed). 1942-1946 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Myer, Dillon S. Speeches. 1942-1946 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings. 1942-1946. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Office Memorandum (mimeographed). Office of the Solicitor: Index-Digest of Opinions... Regional Attorney Opinions (Pacific Coast Region). March 18, 1942-June 30, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Press Releases. 1942-1946 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Relocation Division Memorandum, nos. 25-103. 1942-1946 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Relocation Forum. September-October 1943 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Report (Semi-annual). Includes E.H. Spicer's original notes and drafts. January 1943-June 1946 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
  - Report (Quarterly), 1st-3rd. March-December 1942 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Report (Final). Includes original notes of R.B. Spicer only. 1942-1946 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Reprints and extracts from various publications. 1942-1946 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Reprints from newspapers. 1942-1946 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Resettlement; Reactions. 1942-1946 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Resettlement Brochures. 1942-1946 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Resolutions; Articles Pro and Con on Japanese Relocation. 1942-1946 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Speeches and Radio Broadcasts. 1942-1946 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Thank you letters. 1942-1946 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Administrative Notices: Numbered 1-343. November 1943-March 1946 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
  - Administrative Notices: Unnumbered. June 1942-February 1946 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series II: Newspapers, 1943-1947
  - Daily News Digest. 1944-1946 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
  - Information Digest (for use of the W.R.A. staff). Miscellaneous Numbers. January 1944-September/October 1945 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Washington Daily News Digest (in Japanese). Miscellaneous Issues. May-September 1945 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Newspapers: Doho (Japanese) N.Y., Inside Interior (Department of Interior), Northwest Times ("Only All-English Nisei Newspaper in Pacific Northwest) Seattle, Pacific Citizen (Official Publication of Japanese Americans League), Salt Lake City. 1943-1947. (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Series III: Community Analysis Section Publications, 1943-1946
  - Community Analysis Program (General). 1943-1946 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Community Analysis Program (Final Report - including E.H.Spicer's Notes and Preliminary Drafts). 1943-1946 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Community Analysis Notes, nos. 1-15. 1943-1946 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Project Analysis Series, nos. 1-24. 1943-1946 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Community Analysis Report, nos. 1-19. 1943-1946 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Trends in the Relocation Centers, series II-III. 1943-1946 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Weekly Summary, nos. 1-30. 1943-1946 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Community Analysis Relocation Studies, no. 1. April 1944 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Community Analyst Letter, nos. 1-4. 1943-1946 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Statistic Reports, 1943-1945
  - Office of the Solicitor: A Memorandum on the Validity of Detention Under Leave Regulations of the War Relocation Authority. January 1, 1944 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Leave (Miscellaneous Documents). 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Net Absences on Leave by Centers. Weekly Report. 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Reported Relocation by States. Monthly Report, no. 1-12. 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Returns to West Coast: City (Cumulative); County & Citizenship (Cumulative); Cumulative Summary. 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - Terminal Departures from Centers: Weekly, no. 1-148; Monthly, no. 1-3, 9; Final summary. 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Statistics. 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Series V: Correspondence, 1942-1946
  - Correspondence, A-L. Arranged Alphabetically by Author. 1942-1946 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, M-Z. Arranged Alphabetically by Author. 1942-1946 (Box 11)
- Series VI: Relocation Center Documents, 1943-1946
  - Colorado River Relocation Center, Poston, Arizona: Community Analysis Trend Report, no. 1-88. 1943-1946 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Essays, Notes, Reports, Letters. 1943-1946 (Box 12, Folder 3-5)
  - Miscellaneous Sociological Notes by E.H. Spicer. 1943-1946 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - E.H. Spicer's Anthropology Class (Examinations, Student Papers). 1943-1946 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Central Utah Relocation Center, Topaz, Utah: Community Analysis Reports, nos. 1-74. 1943-1946 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Community Analysis Weekly Trend Reports, nos. 1-41. 1943-1946 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Miscelleaneous Papers. Fort Ontario Emergency Refugee Shelter, Oswego, NY. 1943-1946 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Papers. Gila River Relocation Center, Rivers, Arizona. 1943-1946 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Community Analysis Reports, nos. 1-65. 1943-1946 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Community Analysis Weekly Trend Reports, nos. 1, 7-18. 1943-1946 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Papers. 1943-1946 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Heart Mountain Relocation Center, Heart Mountain, Wyoming: Community Analysis Notes, nos. 1-193. 1943-1946 (Box 14, Folder 1-2)
  - Heart Mountain Relocation Center, Heart Mountain, Wyoming: Community Analyst Trend Report, nos. 1-80. 1943-1946 (Box 14, Folder 3-4)
  - Miscellaneous papers. Includes Report on The Heart Mountain Hospital Walkout. June 24, 1943 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: Community Analysis Reports, nos. 1-105. 1943-1946 (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - Granada Relocation Center, Amache, Colorado: Comunity Analyst Weekly Trend Reports, nos. 1-24. 1943-1946 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Papers. Jerome Relocation Center, Denson, Arkansas. 1943-1946 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Community Analysis Reports, nos. 50, 69, 100, 114, 136. Miscellaneous Papers. Manzanar Relocation Center, Manzanar, California. 1943-1946 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Community Analysis Reports, nos. 1-349. 1943-1946 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Papers. 1943-1946 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Studies by Morris E. Opler: A History of Internal Government at Manzanar, March 1942-December 6, 1942 and The Repatriate-Expatriate Group of Manzanar. 1944 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Minidoka Relocation Center, Hunt, Idaho: Community Analysis Reports, nos. 267-349. 1943-1946 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Papers. Rohwer Relocation Center, Rohwer, Arkansas. 1943-1946 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Community Analyst Weekly Trend Reports, nos. 1-33. 1943-1946 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Papers. Tule Lake Relocation Center, Newell, California. 1943-1946 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Community Analysis Reports, nos. 5, 106, 140, 203, 204. 1943-1946 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Papers. 1943-1946 (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Series VII: Photographs and Publications, 1942-1945
  - Photographs: Relocation Centers. 1942-1945 (Box 17, Folder 1-6)
  - Photographs: War Relocation Authority Officials. 1942-1945 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Photographs: Camp Shelby, Mississippi (442d Combat Team). 1942-1945 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Photographs: Japanese at Work After Resettlement. 1942-1945 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Photographs: Making Mochigoni (a Japanese Bread) at One of the Camps. Includes 31 Assorted Publications about the Japanese by Other Authors than W.R.A. Staff Members. 1942-1945 (Box 17, Folder 10)
- Series VIII: War Relocation Authority Publications and Reports, 1943-1946
  - War Relocation Authority Publications and Reports. 1943-1946 (Box 18)
    Includes:
    Administrative Highlights of the WRA Program. 1946
    Aims and Plans of WRA by D.S. Myer. In Japanese. 1943
    Annual Report of the Director. 1943-1944 and 1944-1945
    By-Product of War by Ruth E. McKee. No Date
    Community Government in War Relocation Centers. 1946
    Education Program in War Relocation Centers. 1945
    The Evacuated People: A Quantitative Description. 1946
    Information for Employees of the War Relcoation Authority. Induction Kit. No Date
    Legal and Constitutional Phases of the WRA Program. 1946?
    Myths and Facts About Japanese Americans. June 1945
    National and Local Organizations and Agencies Maintaining Programs for Japanese Americans: A Directory. June 1946
    New Neighbors Among Us. August 1944
    Nisei in the War Against Japan. April 1945.
    Nisei in Uniform. 1943?
    People in Motion: the Postwar Adjustment of the Evacuated Japanese Americans. 1946?
    Pertinent Facts About Relocation Centers and Japanese Americans. No Date
    Questions and Answers for Evacuees No Date
    Relocating a People. No Date
    Relocating Japanese-American Evacuees. No Date
    Relocating Japanese Americans. May 1945
    Relocation Communities for Wartime Evacuees. September 1942
    Relocation of Japanese-Americans. May 1943
    The Relocation Program. 1946
    The Relocation Program: a Guidebook for the Residents of Relocation Centers. May 1943
    Segregation of Evacuees. No Date
    The Segregation Program: a Statement for Appointed Personnel in WRA Centers. No Date
    Token Shipment: the Story of America's War Refugee Shelter. 1946
    Uprooted Americans in Your Community. May 1945
    WRA: A Story of Human Conservation. 1946
    The War Relocation Work Corps: A Circular of Information for Enlistees and Their Families. No Date
    Wartime Exile: the Exclusion of the Japanese Americans from the West Coast. 1946
    The Wartime Handling of Evacuee Property. 1946
    What We're Fighting For: Statements by United States Servicemen about Americans of Japanese Descent. No Date
    Your Job as Reports Officer. No Date
  - Bohannan, Laura, A., Law and the Japanese in the United States. (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Freed, Anne, The Changing Japanese Family in the United States. (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Freed, Anne, Evacuee Participation in Segregation. 1943 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Freed, Anne, Family Relocation Counseling. General.. 1944 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Freed, Anne, The Issei and Relocation. 1944 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Luomala, Katharine, California Attitudes About the Amount of Publicity Desirable for Returning Evacuees. 1945 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Luomala, Katharine, California Takes Back Its Japanese Evacuees. 1945 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Luomala, Katharine, Community Analysis Outside the Relocation Centers. Paper Given at Society of Applied AnthropologyConference, NYC. May 1946 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Luomala, Katharine, Fellow Californians are Fellow Americans. (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - McKee, Ruth, History of WRA to June 30, 1944.. 1944 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Myer, Dillon S., War Relocation Authority (2 drafts). (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Provinse, John H., The Development of a War-Time Community (2 drafts). 1946 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Provinse, John H., Proposal for a Comparative Study of the Treatment of Persons of Japanese Ancestry During World War II in Mexico, Canada, Hawaii, and Continental United States. 1945 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Sady, Rachel R., Issei Attitudes Toward Japan. 1944 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Sady, Rachel R., Issei Points of View. 1944 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Sady, Rachel R., Plan for Study of Leave Clearance Denials. 1944 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Sady, Rachel R., Sit Tighters. 1945 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Spicer, Edward H., An Analysis of Requests for Repatriation and Expatriation. 1944 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Spicer, Edward H., Current Problems of Japanese American Adjustment. 1945 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Spicer, Edward H., The Effects of Center Life on the Evacuee Population. 1944 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Spicer, Edward H., First Generation Japanese Americans (unfinished). (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Spicer, Edward H., History of the Community Analysis Section. 1945 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Spicer, Edward, H., Japanese Americans Educated in Japan (rough draft). 1944 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Spicer, Edward H., On Being Pushed Around. (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Spicer, Edward H., Racism in Reverse: the Story of the WRA (Final and Several Preliminary Drafts). (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Spicer, Edward H. and others, Impounded People: Japanese Americans in the Relocation Centers (2 drafts). (Box 19, Folder 10-11)
  - DeYoung, John, Chapter IV: Background to the Resettler Community. 1945 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Embree, John F., Dealing with Japanese Americans. 1942 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Kimball, S.T., The Caucasians Make the Rules. 1945? (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Lantis, M., Possible Family Reactions to Liquidation of the Centers. 1944 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - McVoy, Edgar C., Discussion of Relocation Problems. 1943 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Marks, E.B., Factors Influencing Morale in Relocation Centers. 1944 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Mercer, Inez, Suggestions for Job Relations Training at Relocation Centers. 1944 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Powell, John W., American's Refugees: Exodus and Diaspora. 1943 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Rademaker, John A. and Lind, A.W., An Examination of the Underlying Causal Factors Related to the Differences in the Treatment Accorded to Americans of Japanese Ancestry in theContinental United States and in Hawaii. (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Thomas, Dorothy, Study of the Evacuation and Resettlement of Japanese on the West Coast. 1942 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Tynes, Richard, No Time for Hate. (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Bureau of Sociological Research, Colorado River War Relocation Center, The Japanese Family in America. (Box 19, Folder 12)
- Series IX: Government Documents Relating to War Relocation Authority, 1942-1946
  - Bills and Resolutions (House and Senate). 1942-1946 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Material prepared by WRA for Hearings Before the House Committee on Un-American Activities. 1942-1946 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Documents on National Defense Migration. 1942-1946 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Documents on Investigation of Un-American Propaganda Activities in the United States. 1942-1946 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Documents on Ware Relocation Centers. 1942-1946 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Documents on Immigration, Deportation, and Naturalization. 1942-1946 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Documents on the Administration of Alien Property and Tort Claims Against the U.S. 1942-1946 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Documents on Appropriations. 1942-1946 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Documents of the Supreme Court - Cases re Japanese-American Citizens. 1942-1946 (Box 20, Folder 3)